<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Vous aimez le sport?</title>
	<subtitle>Do you like sport?</subtitle>
		<abstract><para>
		In this unit you will learn how to
		<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
			<listitem><para><b>Ask and talk about likes and dislikes</b></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><b>Say what you and others do as a hobby</b></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><b>Talk about the weather</b></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para></abstract>
	<section><title>Before you start</title>
	<para>Once you know a French person well enough you'll find yourself wanting to express your likes
	and dislikes and talk about your hobbies; here are the structures you'll need:</para>
	<para>j'adore I adore, I like</para>
	<para>j'aime beaucoup I like very much</para>
	<para>je n'aime pas I don't like</para>
	<para>je déteste I hate</para>
	<para>je joue I play</para>
	<para>je fais I do</para>
	<para>Talking about the weather is a particularly important aspect of the British way of life;
	you may find it useful to enquire about the weather forecast if you are planning some kind of
	outdoor activity.</para>
	<para>Essayez! Have a go! You are in a shop in France looking for a corkscrew. However, you don't
	know the French word for it. How would you say that you're looking for something to open bottles
	of wine?</para>
	<para>You: ................................................</para>
	<para>Shopkeeper: Ah! Vous voulez un tire-bouchon (a corkscrew)?</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Key words and phrases</title>
	<table colsep="0" rowsep="0"><tgroup cols="2">
	<tbody>
		<row><entry><b>qu'est-ce que vous faites/pratiquez comme sport?</b></entry><entry><i>what sport do you do?</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>vous faites quoi pendant vos loisirs?</b></entry><entry><i>what hobbies do you have?</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>vous_aimez faire du sport?</b></entry><entry><i>do you like doing sport?</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>quelle est votre cuisine preferee?</b></entry><entry><i>which cooking do you prefer?</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>j'adore aller au restaurant</b></entry><entry><i>I love going to the restaurant</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>mon sport prefere est la natation</b></entry><entry><i>swimming is my favourite sport</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>je fais de la natation</b></entry><entry><i>I swim</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>j'aime (beaucoup) ...</b></entry><entry><i>I like (very much) ...</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>jouer au squash</b></entry><entry><i>playing squash</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>la cuisine francaise</b></entry><entry><i>French cooking</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>ecouter de la musique</b></entry><entry><i>listening to music</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>regarder la television</b></entry><entry><i>watching television</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>je n'aime pas ...</b></entry><entry><i>I don't like ...</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>la planche a voile</b></entry><entry><i>windsurfing</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>la musique classique</b></entry><entry><i>classical music</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>me promener a pied</b></entry><entry><i>going for a walk</i></entry></row>

		<row><entry><b>je deteste faire la cuisine</b></entry><entry><i>I hate cooking</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>je joue au tennis</b></entry><entry><i>I play tennis</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>je joue du piano</b></entry><entry><i>I play the piano</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>je prefere l'equitation</b></entry><entry><i>I prefer riding</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>moi, ce que j'aime c'est sortir avec mes_amis</b></entry><entry><i>what I really like is going out with my friends</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>moi, ce que je deteste c'est la viande saignante</b></entry><entry><i>what I really dislike is rare meat</i></entry></row>

		<row><entry><b>quel temps fait-il?</b></entry><entry><i>what's the weather like?</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>il fait beau, mouvais</b></entry><entry><i>the weather is fine, bad</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>il fait chaud, froid</b></entry><entry><i>it is hot, cold</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>le soleil brille</b></entry><entry><i>the sun shines</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>il pleut</b></entry><entry><i>it's raining</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>il neige</b></entry><entry><i>it's snowing</i></entry></row>
	</tbody></tgroup></table>
<note><para>Out of this list of phrases, the three most useful to remember are:</para>
<para><b>Je fais du</b> ... when speaking about hobbies</para>
<para><b>Je joue au</b> ... when talking about sports</para>
<para><b>Je joue du</b> ... when playing an instrument</para></note>
</section>
<section><title>Dialogue</title>
<para>Jane parle de sports et de loisirs avec les Durand.</para>
<para>Jane and the Durands ara talking about sport and hobbies.</para>
<para>Listen to the recording or read the dialogue and then answer the following questions: What's Mrs Durand's
favourite hobby? What sports does Mr Durand do?</para>
	<table rowsep="0"><tgroup cols="2">
		<colspec colwidth="*" colnum="1" />
		<colspec colwidth="5*" colnum="2" />
		<tbody>
		<row><entry><b>Jane</b></entry><entry>Mme Durand, qu'est-ce que vous faites pendant vos loisirs?</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Mme Durand</b></entry><entry>Moi, j'adore faire la cuisine, <b>surtout</b> la cuisine française.</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Jane</b></entry><entry>Et dans la cuisine française, quels sont vos <b>plats favoris</b>?</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Mme Durand</b></entry><entry>Eh bien, j'aime beaucoup faire tous les plats en sauce, en particulier
		<b>le bceuf bourguignon</b> ou <b>le coq au vin</b>. <b>Vous savez</b>, mon mari aime bien manger et bien boire; c'est un
		gourmet et il <b>apprécie</b> ma cuisine ... alors <b>ça fait plasir</b>!</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Jane</b></entry><entry>Et vous, Monsieur Durand, vous_aimez faire la cuisine?</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>M. Durand</b></entry><entry>Moi, <b>je laisse la cuisine</b> à ma femme. Elle la fait très bien.
		Je préfère le sport.</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Jane</b></entry><entry>Quels sports <b>pratiquez</b>-vous?</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>M. Durand</b></entry><entry>Je joue au squash deux fois par semaine après mon travail
		et <b>quand j'ai le temps</b>, je fais de la natation avec les_enfants le samedi, à la piscine de Chatou.</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Mme Durand</b></entry><entry>Tu aimes bien aussi faire de la planche à voile <b>en_été</b>.</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>M. Durand</b></entry><entry>Oui, <b>c'est vrai</b>. J'aime beaucoup la planche à voile surtout quand_il y a
		du <b>vent</b>, mais je déteste en faire quand_il fait froid ou quand_il pleut.</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Mme Durand</b></entry><entry>Et vous Jane, qu'est-ce que vous faites comme sport?</entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>Jane</b></entry><entry>Oh moi, je pratique un peu tous les sports: le badminton, le tennis
		et quelquefois l'équitation, mais je n'ai pas beaucoup de temps pour faire du sport.</entry></row>
	</tbody>
	</tgroup>
	</table>
<note>
<para>surtout mainly</para>
<para>plats favoris favourite dishes</para>
<para>le bceuf bourguignon beef stew with wine</para>
<para>le coq au vin chicken cooked in wine</para>
<para>vous savez you know</para>
<para>boire to drink</para>
<para>il apprécie he appreciates</para>
<para>ça fait plaisir it is a pleasure</para>
<para>je laisse la cuisine I leave the cooking</para>
<para>pratiquer to do</para>
<para>quand j'ai le temps when I have the time</para>
<para>et_été in summer</para>
<para>c'est vrai it's true</para>
<para>le vent the wind</para>
</note>
</section>

<section><title>Grammar</title>
<section><title>ASKING AND SAYING WHAT YOU DO AS A HOBBY</title>
<simpara>In French to answer questions such as <b>qu'est-ce que vous faites comme sport?</b>
<i>what do you do in the way of sport?</i> or <b>qu'est-ce que vous faites pendant vos loisirs?</b>
<i>what are your hobbies?</i> use <b>je fais de ...</b> or <b>je joue à ...</b> if it is a game.
If you play a musical instrument use <b>je joue de</b>.</simpara>
<simpara>Je fais <b>de la</b> natation et <b>du</b> surf. <i>I swim and I surf.</i></simpara>
<simpara>Je joue <b>au</b> tennis et <b>à la</b> pétanque. <i>I play tennis and petanque (kind of bowls played in the South of France).</i></simpara>
<simpara>Je joue <b>du</b> piano et <b>de la</b> trompette. <i>I play the piano and the trumpet.</i></simpara>
</section>

<section><title>LIKES AND DISLIKES</title>
<simpara>To express your tastes and feelings, you can use <b>aimer</b> (to like, to love) or the two
extremes <b>adorer</b> and <b>détester</b>:</simpara>
<simpara><b>j'adore</b> aller au restaurant</simpara>
<simpara><b>j'aime (beaucoup)</b> jouer au squash, cuisiner, écouter des disques, regarder la télé, la planche à voile</simpara>
<simpara><b>je n'aime pas</b> la planche à voile, la musique classique, me promener à pied</simpara>
<simpara><b>je déteste</b> faire la cuisine</simpara>

<simpara>To say what you like/dislike doing, add the infinitive after j'aime, j'adore, je déteste, je préfère:
je déteste faire de la bicyclette: I hate cycling.</simpara>

<simpara>Include the article <b>le, la, les</b> when making generalizations:</simpara>
<simpara>J'aime les fromages français. I like French cheese.</simpara>
<simpara>L'historie est plus_intéressante que la géographie. History is more interesting than geography.</simpara>

<simpara>When stating likes/dislikes you will often hear French people use the following structures: using <b>ce que</b></simpara>
<simpara><b>Moi, ce que j'aime c'est</b> sortir avec mes_amis.</simpara>
<simpara><b>Moi, ce que je déteste c'est</b> la viande saignante.</simpara>
<simpara><b>Moi, ce que j'adore c'ut</b> soritr le samedi soir.</simpara>
<note><simpara>If you like going out in the evenings, you will find the verb <b>sortir</b> useful
to talk about your outings.</simpara></note>
</section>

<section><title>PRONOUNS: LE, LA, LES IT, HIM, HER, THEM</title>
<simpara>The pronouns <b>le</b> (it, him), <b>la</b> (it, her), <b>les</b> (them) are used to avoid unnecessary repetitions
of nouns; they are placed before the verb to which they refer:</simpara>
<simpara>Vous connaissez <b>M. Durand</b>? Do you know Mr Durand?</simpara>
<simpara>Oui, je <b>le</b> connais. Yes, I know him.</simpara>
<simpara>Vous prenez <b>la carte postale</b>? Are you taking the postcard?</simpara>
<simpara>Oui, je <b>la</b> prends. Yes, I'm taking it.</simpara>
<simpara>Vous_achetez <b>ces foulards</b>? Are you buying these scarves?</simpara>
<simpara>Oui, je <b>les</b>_achète. Yes, I'm buying them.</simpara>
<simpara>Vous_aimez <b>le thé</b>? Do you like tea?</simpara>
<simpara>Oui, je <b>l</b>'aime. Yes, I like it.</simpara>

<simpara><b>L</b>'replaces <b>le</b> or <b>la</b> when the next word starts with a vowel or silent <b>h</b>.
In a negative sentence, <b>l', le, la, les</b> come between the <b>ne</b> or <b>n'</b> and the verb:</simpara>
<simpara>Vous préférez le tennis? Do you prefer tennis?</simpara>
<simpara>Non, je ne le préfére pas. No, I don't prefer if.</simpara>

<note><simpara>Using the pronouns before the verb takes a bit of getting used to and it will take you
a while before you can do it easily. At this early stage just notice them when you hear them in a conversation.</simpara></note>
</section>

<section><title>MORE NEGATIVES</title>
<simpara>You saw in Unit 3 (???) how to make a statement negative in French, using <b>ne ... pas</b>:</simpara>
<simpara>Je <b>n</b>'ai <b>pas</b> d'enfants. I have no children.</simpara>
<simpara>There are other negatives you can use:</simpara>
<simpara><b>ne ... plus</b> no more/no longer</simpara>
<simpara><b>ne ... rien</b> nothing</simpara>
<simpara><b>ne ... jamais</b> never</simpara>
<simpara><b>ne ... que</b> only</simpara>
<simpara>Je n'ai plus de vin. I have no more wine.</simpara>
<simpara>Il ne veut rien. He wants nothing.</simpara>
<simpara>Il n'a jamais d'argent. He never has any money.</simpara>
<simpara>Je n'ai que dix_euros. I've only got ten euros.</simpara>
</section>

<section><title>'TO KNOW': WHEN TO USE SAVOIR, WHEN TO USE CONNAîTRE</title>
<simpara>There are two verbs for knowing: <b>savoir</b> and <b>connaître</b>.</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
	<listitem><para>Use <b>savoir</b> (on its own) to say that you know or don't know a fact:</para>
	<para><b>Je sais à quelle heure part le train.</b> I know when the train leaves.</para>
	<para><b>Je ne sais pas où est l'arrêt d'autobus.</b> I don't know where the bus stop is.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem><para>Use <b>savoir</b> followed by the infinitive to say that you know how to do something:</para>
	<para><b>Je sais faire la cuisine.</b> I know how to cook.</para>
	<para><b>Vous savez faire du ski?</b> Do you know how to ski?</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para><b>Connaître</b> is used to say that you know people and places:</para>
	<para><b>Je connais Paris.</b> I know Paris.</para>
	<para><b>Dupuis combien de temps est-ce que vous le connaissez?</b> How long have you known him?</para>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</section>

<section><title>QUEL TEMPS FAIT-IL? WHAT'S THE WEATHER LIKE?</title>
<simpara>The easiest way to talk about the weather is to start with <b>il fait</b>:</simpara>
<simpara><b>il fait beau, mouvais</b> it's fine, the weather is bad</simpara>
<simpara><b>il fait froid, chaud</b> it's cold, hot</simpara>
<simpara><b>il fait du vent</b> it's windy</simpara>
<simpara><b>il fait du brouillard</b> it's foggy</simpara>
<simpara><b>il fait (du) soleil</b> it's sunny</simpara>
<simpara><b>il pleut</b> it's raining</simpara>
<simpara><b>il neige</b> it's snowing</simpara>
<simpara><b>le soleil brille</b> the sun is shining</simpara>
</section>
</section>

</chapter>