<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Pour aller à ...?</title>
	<subtitle>The way to ...?</subtitle>
		<abstract><para>
		In this unit you will learn
		<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
			<listitem><para><b>How to count from 90 upwards</b></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><b>How to ask for and understand directions</b></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><b>Useful verbs to describe what you do every day</b></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para></abstract>
	<section><title>Before you start</title>
	<para>In <b>Key words and phrases</b>, Unit 4, you learnt to say how far somewhere is and how long
	it takes to go somewhere on foot and by train. Revise these structures as you will need them to
	understand the dialogue in this unit.</para>
	<para>You now know how to ask where things are: <b>Où est ...?</b> or <b>C'est où ...?</b> Asking the way is also
	very simple; you start your question with the phrase <b>pour aller à</b> and raise the voice at the end
	of the statement.</para>
	<para>Understanding the answer can be more tricky and you'll need to pick out the few essential
	words such as <b>tout droit</b>, <b>à gauche</b>, <b>à droite</b> out of the flow of other words.</para>
	<para>As people give you directions, repeat after them, to make sure you have understood. If you do
	not understand, ask them to repeat or slow down.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Key words and phrases</title>
	<table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody>
		<row><entry><b>pour_aller à ...</b></entry><entry><i>the way to ...</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>(vous) allez tout droit</b></entry><entry><i>(you) go straight on</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>continuez</b></entry><entry><i>carry on</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>descendez la rue</b></entry><entry><i>go down the street</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>montez l'avenue</b></entry><entry><i>go up the avenue</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>passez le magasin</b></entry><entry><i>go beyond the shop</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>traversez la place</b></entry><entry><i>cross the square</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>prenez la route de ...</b></entry><entry><i>take the road to ...</i></entry></row>

		<row><entry><b>(vous) tournez à gauche</b></entry><entry><i>(you) turn left</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>tournez à droite</b></entry><entry><i>turn right</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>vous_allez prendre ...</b></entry><entry><i>you're going to take ...</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>la première rue à droite</b></entry><entry><i>the first street on the right</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>la deuxième sur votre gauche</b></entry><entry><i>the second on your left</i></entry></row>
		
		<row><entry><b>la place du marché est située ...</b></entry><entry><i>the market place is ...</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>au coin de la rue</b></entry><entry><i>at the corner of the street</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>à côté du supermarché</b></entry><entry><i>next to the supermarket</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>en face de la boulangerie</b></entry><entry><i>opposite the baker's</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>au centre ville</b></entry><entry><i>in the town centre</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>sur votre gauche</b></entry><entry><i>on your left</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>sur, sous</b></entry><entry><i>on, under</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>devant, derrière</b></entry><entry><i>in front of, behind</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>dans</b></entry><entry><i>in, inside</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>entre</b></entry><entry><i>between</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>il faut combien de temps?</b></entry><entry><i>how long does it take?</i></entry></row>
		<row><entry><b>il faut environ 25 minutes</b></entry><entry><i>you need about 25 minutes</i></entry></row>
	</tbody></tgroup></table>
	<section><title>NUMBERS OVER 90</title>
	<table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-dix 90</entry><entry>cent 100</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-onze 91</entry><entry>cent un 101</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-douze 92</entry><entry>cent deux 102</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-treize 93</entry><entry>cent vingt-trois 123</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-quatorze 94</entry><entry>cinq cent trente-quatre 534</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-quinze 95</entry><entry>mille 1000</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-seize 96</entry><entry>mille neuf cent quinze 1915</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-dix-sept 97</entry><entry>deux mille 2000</entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-dix-huit 98</entry><entry></entry></row>
		<row><entry>quatre-vingt-dix-neuf 99</entry><entry></entry></row>
	</tbody></tgroup></table>
	</section>
	<section><title>Dialogue</title>
	<para>Jane passe la journée chez les Durand. L'après-midi, elle décide d'aller au centre ville du Chatou.</para>
	<para>Jane is spending the day with the Durands. She decides to go to the town centre in the afternoon.</para>
	<para>While you listen to the recording, look at the street map (le plan de ville) of Chatou with Activity 2. How
	do you get from M. Durand's house to the park and how long does it take to walk there?</para>
	<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
	<listitem><para>Jane : M. Durand, avez-vous un plan de Chatou? Je voudrais_aller <b>d'abord</b> au parc et puis, <b>si j'ai le temps</b>, dans les magasins ...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>M. Durand : Voici le plan. Vous pouvez <b>le garder</b> car j'en_ai deux.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Jane : Merci beaucoup. Ou est le parc de Chatou?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>M. Durand : <b>Voyons</b>, nous sommes_ici sur le plan. Vous tournez à gauche, <b>en sortant de la maison</b>, vous_allez
	jusqu'au bout de la rue Vaugirard, vous tournez à droite dans la rue Vincennes et puis c'est sur votre
	gauche à 200 mètres.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Jane : Bon, alors, à gauche en sortant puis je tourne à droite et c'est sur ma gauche ... C'est loin à pied?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>M. Durand : Non, pas très loin; il faut environ 25 minutes.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Jane : Oh là là, c'est <b>trop loin</b> pour moi. Euh, on peut y aller en_autobus?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>M. Durand : Oui, oui. L'arrêt d'autobus est situé juste au coin de la rue Vaugirard. C'est très
	pratique et il y a un autobus toutes les dix minutes.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Jane : Je voudrais aussi <b>faire des_achats</b> pour moi et acheter quelques souvenirs pour ma famille en
	Grande-Bretagne et au Canada.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>M. Durand : Eh bien, vous pouvez_aller au <b>centre commercial</b>. Il est sur la place du marché à côté
	de la gare. Vous_avez un_autobus direct. Il va du parc au centre commercial.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Jane : Bon, je pars tout de suite ... j'ai beaucoup de choses à acheter et ... je voudrais rentrer vers
	19 heures.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<note>
	<para><b>d'abord</b> firstly</para>
	<para><b>si j'ai le temps</b> if I have the time</para>
	<para><b>voici</b> here is ...</para>
	<para><b>le garder</b> keep it</para>
	<para><b>voyons</b> let's see</para>
	<para><b>en sortant de la maison</b> as you leave the house</para>
	<para><b>trop loin</b> too far</para>
	<para><b>faire des_achats</b> to do some shopping</para>
	<para><b>le centre commercial</b> the shopping centre</para>
	</note>
	</section>
	</section>
	<section><title>Grammar</title>
	<section><title>ASKING THE WAY AND GIVING DIRECTIONS</title>
	<para><b>Pour_aller à</b> (<i>to get to</i>) is a very useful structure to remember. Used in a questioning tone
	it means <i>How do I/we get to ...?</i></para>
	<para><b>Pardon, Monsieur, pour_aller à Gordes?</b> Excuse me, Sir, how do we get to Gordes?</para>
	<para><b>Pour_aller à Gordes, prenez la route pour St. Saturnin.</b> To get to Gordes, take the road to St. Saturnin.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>ALLER TO GO PARTIR TO LEAVE</title>
	<para>Here are two very useful verbs. Both verbs are irregular, and <b>aller</b> is particularly
	useful as it is used when speaking about the future (explained in Unit 10):</para>
	<table><tgroup cols="2"><tbody>
		<row><entry>aller to go</entry><entry>partir to leave</entry></row>
		<row><entry>je vais</entry><entry>je pars</entry></row>
		<row><entry>tu vas</entry><entry>tu pars</entry></row>
		<row><entry>il/elle/on va</entry><entry>il/elle/on part</entry></row>
		<row><entry>nous allons</entry><entry>nous partons</entry></row>
		<row><entry>vous allez</entry><entry>vous partez</entry></row>
		<row><entry>ils/elles vont</entry><entry>ils/elles partent</entry></row>
	</tbody></tgroup></table>
	<para>Vous_<b>allez</b> jusqu'au bout de la rue. You go to the end of the road.</para>
	<para>Je voudrais <b>aller</b> à la banque. I would like to go to the bank.</para>
	<para>Je <b>pars</b> tout de suite. I'm leaving immediately.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>UNDERSTANDING DIRECTIONS</title>
	<para>Understanding directions can be trickier than asking the way as the directions can sound
	complicated, so it is important to pick out the essential words:</para>
	<para>As an answer to your question, you'll probably hear one of the following constructions:</para>
	<para><b>prenez</b> take; <b>descendez</b> go down; <b>tournez à</b> turn; <b>allez</b> go; <b>montez</b> go up</para>
	<para><b>Il faut prendre ...</b> You have to (lit. it's necessary to) take</para>
	<para><b>Il faut descendre ...</b> You have to go down ...</para>
	<para><b>Il faut tourner ...</b> You have to turn ...</para>
	<para><b>Il faut aller ...</b> You have to go ...</para>
	<para><b>Il faut monter ...</b> You have to go up ...</para>
	
	<para>The <b>t</b> in <b>droite</b> <i>right</i> is sounded but it is not in <b>droit</b> <i>straight</i>.
	<b>Droit</b> is usually preceded by <b>tout</b>: <b>tout droit</b> <i>straight on</i>.
	<b>Droite</b> is preceded by <b>à</b> or <b>sur la</b>: <b>à droite</b>, <b>sur la droite</b>:</para>
	<para>Il faut aller <b>tout droit</b>. You have to go straight on.</para>
	<para>La gare est <b>sur la droite</b>. The station is on the right.</para>
	
	<para>You may be unlucky when asking directions and find that you are asking a tourist! His answer
	would be <b>je ne sais pas</b> (I don't know), or <b>je ne suis pas d'ici</b> (I am not from here).</para>
	
	<para>If you don't understand the information, e.g. the address, the street name, or the number
	of the building you are given, use the structure <b>c'est quel(le) ...?</b> (Unit 3) to have the
	information repeated:</para>
	<para><b>C'est quelle rue?</b> Which street is it?</para>
	<para><b>C'est quel numéro?</b> Which number is it?</para>
	<para><b>C'est quelle adresse?</b> Which address is it?</para>
	
	<note><para>Out of this whole section the most useful expression for you to remember is <b>Pour aller à ...</b>
	when you want to ask the way. To make sure that you understand the directions, repeat them aloud
	as they are given to you. You can always ask people to repeat or slow down.</para></note>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>WHEN TO USE A; WHEN TO USE EN</title>
	<para>To say that you are in town or you are going/want to go to a town, always use <b>à</b> (with an
	accent to differentiate it from <b>a</b> <i>has</i>). Study the examples below:</para>
	<para><b>Je suis à Bordeaux.</b> I'm in Bordeaux.</para>
	<para><b>Nous_allons à Bordeaux.</b> We're going to Bordeaux.</para>
	
	<para>To say that you are in a country or you're going to a country, use <b>en</b> with feminine
	countries (often finishing with an <b>-e</b>) and <b>au/aux</b> with the others:</para>
	<para><b>Je suis en_Australie.</b> I am in Australia.</para>
	<para><b>Je vais en_Angleterre.</b> I'm going to England.</para>
	<para><b>Vous_allez au Canada.</b> You're going to Canada.</para>
	
	<para>The country is preceded by its article in sentences such as:</para>
	<para><b>Je connais bien la Suisse.</b> I know Switzerland quite well.</para>
	<para><b>J'aime beaucoup le Portugal.</b> I like Portugal a lot.</para>
	
	<note><para>So... it's easy! Use <b>à</b> before towns and <b>en</b> before countries, or <b>au</b> with the few
	masculine ones.</para></note>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>WHEN À (AT, TO, IN, ON) IS FOLLOWED BY LE, LA, L', LES ...</title>
	<para>The preposition <b>à</b> followed by a definite article (<b>le, la, l', les</b>) changes its form in the following way:</para>
	<para><b>à + le</b> becomes <b>au</b></para>
	<para><b>à + la</b> remains <b>à + la</b></para>
	<para><b>à + l'</b> remains <b>à + l'</b></para>
	<para><b>à + les</b> becomes <b>aux</b></para>
	
	<para>Pour_aller <b>au musée</b> du Louvre, s'il vous plaît? Which way to the Louvre Museum please?</para>
	<para>Nous_allons <b>à l'église</b> St. Paul. We are going to St. Paul's Church.</para>
	<para>Il arrive <b>à la gare</b> à huit heures du matin. He arrives at the station at eight o'clock in the morning.</para>
	<para>Il va <b>aux_Etats-Unis</b> deux fois par mois. He goes to the United States twice a month.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>LOCATING THE EXACT SPOT</title>
	<para>Remember that when <b>de</b> is used in combination with <b>le, la, l', les</b> in expressions such as
	<b>en face de</b> <i>opposite</i>, <b>à côté de</b> <i>next to</i>, <b>au coin de</b> <i>at the corner of</i>,
	<b>près de</b> <i>near</i>, you need to change its form (Unit 2):</para>
	<para>au coin <b>du parc</b> <i>at the corner of the park</i></para>
	<para>près <b>des grands magasins</b> <i>near the department stores</i></para>
	<para>en face <b>de la piscine</b> <i>opposite the swimming pool</i></para>
	<para>à côté <b>de l'office du tourisme</b> <i>next to the tourist office</i></para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>PREMIER, DEUXIÈME, TROISIÈME FIRST, SECOND, THIRD</title>
	<para>If you are directed to the 3rd floor, the 2nd street and so on, the numbers end in <b>-ième</b>:</para>
	<para><b>deuxième</b> second; <b>troisième</b> third; <b>quatrième</b> fourth; <b>dixième</b> tenth</para>
	<para>But, <i>first</i> is <b>premier</b> before all masculine nouns, and <b>première</b> before all feminine nouns:</para>
	<para>Vous montez au <b>premier</b> étage. You go up to the first floor.</para>
	<para>C'est la <b>première</b> porte. It's the first door.</para>
	<para>Vous prenez la <b>deuxième</b> à gauche. You take the second on the left.</para>
	<para>C'est le <b>troisième</b> bâtiment. It's the third building.</para>
	</section>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Activities</title>
	<para>Now listen to the replies of the passer-by on the recording and work out which letter on the map
	represents each of these places. If you haven't got the recording, read the replies below:</para>
	<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
	<listitem><para>C'est très facile. Vous montez la rue Vincennes et vous prenez la première à gauche.
	Le piscine se trouve sur votre droite, en face du parc.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Bon, pour la gare, continuez tout droit, toujours tout droit. Juste avant le pont,
	tournez à droite et vous_êtes dans la rue Thiers. La gare est_à côté du centre commercial.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>L'èglise St Paul? Eh bien, c'est tout droit, à 100 mètres d'ici, sur votre dorite,
	au coin de la rue Fleurus.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Euh - attendez vous - il faut tourner tout de suite à droite puis descendez la rue
	Fleurus et le musée est_à 10 minutes à pied sur votre gauche à côté de l'Hôtel Colbert.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Vous_allez tout droit jusqu'au pont. Juste avant le pont tournez à gauche et l'office
	du tourisme se trouve à côté d'une pharmacie.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	
	<para>Now it's your turn to practise giving directions. Use the text above as a model but you don't
	have to answer exactly like it; for example instead of <b>vous montez/descendez la rue</b> you can say
	<b>(vous) allez/continuez tout droit</b>. Here are the questions:</para>
	<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha" spacing="compact">
	<listitem><para>Pardon Monsieur, pour_aller à la piscine?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>S'il vous plaît Madame, je voudrais aller au musée; pouvez-vous me dire où il se trouve?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Pardon Monsieur, savez-vous où est l'office du tourisme?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Pardon Mademoiselle, je ne suis pas d'ici ... euh, il y a un centre commercial à Chatou?</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	
	<para>Look at the <b>centre commercial de Chatou</b> and fill in the blanks using the words from
	the list below.</para>
	<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha" spacing="compact">
	<listitem><para>La poste est <b>en face du</b> café.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>La café est <b>à côté de la</b> pâtisserie.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>L'office du tourisme est <b>au coin de</b> la place François 1er.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>La pharmacie est <b>entre</b> la poste et la banque.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>L'église est <b>au bout de</b> la rue Thiers.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Les <b>grands magasins</b> sont en face du supermarché.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Le <b>bar</b> est à côté de l'hôtel.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>La <b>pâtisserie</b> est entre le café et l'office du tourisme.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>La pharmacie est <b>dans la rue</b> Thiers.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Le supermarché est <b>sur la place</b> François 1er.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	</section>
</chapter>
